{
  "reference_number": "598",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Setting a goal to set a target is silly. That's just kicking the can down the road."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "Short lived gases like methane will have a much quicker impact on the climate and should be prioritised over carbon. Definitely don't\n\n ignore short lived cases and focus exclusively on carbon, just because carbon has all the media attention."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Carbon trading is far too likely to result in cheating."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But only in exceptional circumstances."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Companies should be able to have some ability to plan for the changes without the risk that they might be changed by a new\n government."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, although the government shouldn't just be able to declare something to be \"exceptional circumstances\". So, e.g. if the economy\ntakes a hit, that shouldn't be a licensing to change the budget. Only truly exceptional circumstances should allow a change, and\n\nthere should be a list of examples of such circumstances written into the legisation."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, although the potentially disastrous long term consequences of climate change should be weight up against all these other\nfactors."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The huge impact of animal agriculture on climate change is mostly overlooked.\n\nhttps://www.theguardian.com/environment/2014/jul/21/giving-up-beef-reduce-carbon-footprint-more-than-cars This is, of course,\nhugely unpopular as most people in New Zealand consume meat and a large portion of the NZ economy is based on raising\n\nlivestock. However, the reality of the situation is that a reduction in meat production and consumption will have the biggest short term\nimpact on climate change, so it would be foolish and irresponsible for the government to ignore this. A potential solution would be to\nput in place measures to transition the NZ economy to be more focused on technology development and high-value organic\n\nvegetable production. The same fields were cows currently live could be converted to vegetable farms. This might even increase the\nfarmers' revenue as there is a large international trend towards vegetarianism: http://www.roymorgan.com/findings/6663-vegetarians-\n\non-the-rise-in-new-zealand-june-2015-201602080028 A side-benefit of this kind of economic shift could be an improvement in the\nhealth of New Zealanders. That is, consuming more vegetables leading to less heart diseases, for example."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "With the USA and China not doing much to counter climate change, New Zealand alone can't have much impact. Adaption is a must."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Very much so."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Some specific policies to consider: - Subsidies and tax incentives to encourage renewable power and electric vehicle (including\nebikes) - Increased tariffs and tax on animal products and discounts on vegetable products - Investing in a smart grid that can handle\n\ndistributed power production - Setting goals to shift New Zealand's economy to be more sustainable - Aiming to reach carbon zero\nearlier than 2050"
    }
  ]
}
